Tekstet av Nicolai Winther
Pre ор
On the Tae pickup artists living natural
This exhibition was planned to commemorate
the end of the war. The works of the
painters who played an active part in the
United States, Kuniyoshi Yasuo, Henry
Sugimoto, and Usui Bunpei, are exhibited.
中でも一際目を引くのが、
共生収容所の中で描かれた日系人画家たちの作品です。
彼らは収容所の中で屈辱に耐えながら、
絵画によって希望を見出そうと絵筆を取りました。
KONNICHIWA
でも50年間くらいから50年間くらいにあんなにたくさんの方が向こうに渡って絵を描いていたという事実は僕もある意味では初めてで非常にびっくりしたんですよね。
尾端千代という名前はご存知でした?
全然知らなかったんですよ。やっぱり非常に印象的で素晴らしい絵を描いていらっしゃるので、なんで今まで知らなかったんだろうと思って非常に自分の不勉強を恥じたという。
I also first met Obata Chura, but he had
been drawing pictures to protect his
culture and humanity in the camp. Obata
Chura was the leader. Obata Chura had a
great influence on the American art
movement on the West Coast. I went to the
West Coast to investigate. I went to the U
.S. to interview them.
San Francisco, the west coast of the U.S.
This town, which had many Japanese
immigrants since ancient times, became the
stage of the activities of Chihura Obata
and his friends.
The non-fiction writer Tetsuro Shimojima
Shimojima-san has been interviewing
Japanese painters of the Shuyo-jo for more
than 10 years. Shimojima-san says that he
discovered something unexpected in the
life of the Shuyo-jo while visiting the
Shuyo-jo many times and listening to the
people involved.
下の話を聞くうちに収容所の生活に意外な側面があったことを発見したと下島さんは言います。
4年間という長い収容所生活が絵のために非常に充実し、
そしてむしろ楽しんだというようなことをおっしゃる人が多数いらっしゃるんですね。
収容所時代が充実していたと。 そうですね。 I was surprised and
surprised to find that I met a painter
called Chihura Obata about three years
ago.
日本画家小畑千浦は1903年、明治36年にアメリカに渡りました。 Sumiei-ya
Suisai-ga-de Nishi-kaigan-no-Bijitsukai-no
-Chumoku-o-Atsume, Nochi-ni California-Dai
-gaku Barclay-ko-no-Kyo-ju-ni-Batteki-sa
-remashita.
Obata Chiura-ga-nakunaru-made-sunde-ita
Barclay-no-ie-wo-tazure-mashita.
Hello! Konnichiwa!
Nice to see you again! Og Ova-san, ojou
-san, yuri-san. Yurisakun. Yoroshiku
onegai shimasu. Sakurai desu, Najimichi.
Oma-san. Nice to meet you. Sakurai desu,
yoroshiku onegai shimasu, Najimichi.
Please come in. Ega demo arimasu ka? Hai.
Si, koshika. Are mo so desu ka? So, papa
ga kakimashita. Magnolia to Blue Jay.
Magnolia. Mokuren no hana. So, so. Hanan
to, tori tote mo suki datta no kaku no.
Ah, ok. Ah, I drew a CG. There was no
studio. She was always surrounded by her
family and drew in the dining room.
So this is the place where you used to sit
in your studio? Yes. Where did you sit? I
sat here, and the windows were all open. I
really liked to work here. ここでやるの。 はい。 へえ。
どんなふうにして描いてらしたんでしょうね。 思えてらっしゃいますか?
そう。パパはベースボールとっても好きだった。 野球が。
そう。だから、レディオを耳に入れて、こうやって描いて。 聞きながら?
そう。時々ジャイアンツが負けると、はーって怒って。 自分で。 I was
writing a poem, but it was no good. That
might have happened.
Obata Chiura was born in 1885, in the year
of 18, in Okayama.
His real name is Sato Zoroku.
千代に住む兄六一の養子になりました。
千代七歳の時の絵です。
もともと絵の得意だった千代は、日本画家だった六一の影響を受け、自らも画家になることを決意します。
Chura, who was taught by Rokuichi, was
only 17 years old when he won the Japanese
Art Museum's Grand Prize, and won the
first prize. However, the following year,
he suddenly went to the United States.
The world is wide, and there are tens of
millions of people.
人たちがいます。 Chiu-la's book is his.
Chiu-la, who has been to the U.S., starts
his life by drawing schoolboys and日経新聞
illustrations. 日々の生活を始めます。
都米して9年目、27歳の時に書いた千浦書記の代表作です。
大地に立つおゆうしい少女は、結婚して間もない新妻、春子です。
薄草とした杉木立ち。
太い幹や枝の一本一本が墨の濃淡によって巧みにかき分けられています。
足元には大地から生命を受けた小さな草が群生し、花を結んでいます。
Haruko's expectation and anxiety, which
had already taken over her new life, are
symbolically depicted in the transparent
air at dawn.
Chihura, who opened the new territory of
Japanese painting in the United States,
was inspired by his creative will and
traveled over the years seeking new
themes.
His vast works remained in the basement
warehouse.
Where did you draw this painting? This is
a painting that was done in Yosemite
Valley 1938, right before the war. You're
drawing Yosemite? Right. Grandpa used to
go to the valley every summer for camping.
Oh, every summer. And sketching and
painting and of course fishing. Of course.
That's pre-war, isn't it?
A storm that strikes the warning of
Yosemite National Park.
It is a dynamic picture of the dramatic
changes of nature.
1927年尾端千浦はカリフォルニア大学バークレー校の美術教授ワースライダーと共に寄せ見てを訪れました。そして2ヶ月にわたってキャンプ生活をしながら寄せ見ての大自然を描きました。
At that time, Yosemite was the
representative national treasure of
America, and was written by many painters.
However, Yosemite, written by Japanese
painter Obata Chiura, made the Americans
feel the appearance of Yosemite that had
never been seen before.
Chiura's Yosemite series further enhanced
his reputation.
"-The
Monterey Monterey to the south. Matsu is
in the middle. It's very Japanese. Chiura
grew up in Sendai from the age of 5. I
think the scenery of Matsushima Bay is
left in the corner of his head. The name
Chiura was also taken from Matsushima Bay.
Adidoma Aloken temple Cliele BAKUREIKO,
BIRTHDAY Obata Chiura, who returned from
Yosemite, was invited as a Japanese artist
teacher at this university.
If you want to draw rain, be struck by
rain. If you want to draw wind, be blown
by wind. And draw through thousands of
lenses of your heart.
Chiura's lecture was strongly supported by
the students.
Chiura's painting is still there.
This tower is one of them. It's called the
Cesar Tower.
It's a wonderful tower. It matches the
blue sky so well.
What kind of memories did you have when
you saw this tower that is stretched out
in the sky? Nå er det en dag som Overture
har pågått på en ståndskraftig rute. Det
var en dag som var pågått på en
ståndskraftig rute. Den var pågått på en
ståndskraftig rute.
木の字に岩絵の具で描かれた山上の湖。
千浦ブルーと呼ばれた青が幾重にも塗り重ねられ、湖の神秘を際立たせています。
Teksting av Nicolai
Winther
線と色彩で躍動的な女性たちを描き出しています。
1930年代、アメリカでは新しい美術の動きが出ていました。
This work also has an influence on the US
abstract expressionism of the time.
Obata Chiura is an artist who has
beautifully fused the two different
cultures of the United States and Japan.
美好に融合させた芸術家だと思います。
サンフランシスコの作家マキシンホン・キングストンがこう言っています。
日本の風景を見て訓練を積んできた尾端教授の目には、
モントレーやヨセミテの風景の中に、
本当のカリフォルニアの姿がくっきりと見えていたと。 全くその通りで、 Kare ni
wa sono fukie no motsu Mottomo shiteki na
shunkan o toraeru me ga Sonawatte ita no
desu
1941年 Taiheiyo sensou ga hajimaru chokuzen
ni kakareta Jisuberi
崩れ去っていく土砂の中央に身を寄せる小さな人々の姿に、日系人たちの不安が表現されています。
1942年2月、ルーズベルト大統領令によって、西海岸の日系人およそ12万人が、適正外国人として強制収容されることになりました。
Obata Chura is also admitted to a
temporary shelter in Tampolan, south of
San Francisco, with his family. Do you
remember the day you were gathered at the
Tampolan meeting place? Yes, it was
raining that day. I was very sad. I took a
bus to Tampolan at Bay Bridge. I went to
Nashville and came to Tampere. I put my
horse in the stable. The old horse? Yes. I
was thirteen at that time, so I loved
horses very much. I rode a cheeser. I was
happy to be living in the stable.
Were you happy? Yes. Mama gakkari shite,
bed ga, army no bed ga atte, mattress,
straw ga haitte. Wara ga atte, ne. Sokko
ni swatte, mama naiteshimatta. Mama, she
never nakanai shito datte, tottemo tsuo i.
Taka watashi bikkuri shite, naze naiteru?
de ttitta. I was so sad to see my mother
living in a horse shed. I never thought
about that.
They often called it a mud sea. It was a
terrible sea.
泥に足を取られ、あえぎあえぎやっと馬小屋へ転がり込んで、果たして泣かなかった者が幾人あろう。
そして我々のタンフォーランにおける生活が始められた。
日本を遠く離れ、異郷の地で永遠と築いてきた者すべてを失ってしまった日系人たち。
Obata Chiura remembers the opening
ceremony of the art school,
The opening ceremony was the 25th day
since the end of the school.
I left the city where I had lived for many
years, and entered a life that was similar
to the encounter of the grasslands.
日々を新たなる希望を持っていかなくてはいけません。
以上の趣旨で、ここにタンフォーラン美術学校を設立いたします。
日系人の誇りをもって生きよう 勇気をもとう
尾端中羅の呼びかけは大きな共感を呼び
やがて生徒は数百人にも上りました
Mere mokai kotomo, about six years old,
ojisan, obasan, minna kimashita kakko ni,
yorokonde minna kimashita yo. Haite sugu
warito dekita nesu. So, tomodachi,
Berkeley no professor and students ni
tanonde kami to enogu to fude naka minna
okutte chodai te tanomi mashita. I brought
my friends and started.
When the camp was completed in the whole
of the United States, the Nikkei people
were moved to other places. In September
1942, Chura Obata was sent to the Tophaz
camp in the Yuta-shu desert area with his
family. 宗洋所へ送られました。
吉浦はここにも美術学校を作ったのです。
私の目の前のこの有志鉄線、
この有志鉄線が宗洋所の鉄線です。
50年前の鉄線が今も残っていました。
この鉄線のこちら側が宗洋所の敷地で、
広大な砂漠の中に薔薇が立ち並んでいたのです。 I can see nothing
but Topaz over there. The name of the
place is just the origin of the name.
I'm standing in the area where the art
school is.
砂漠地帯の真ん中に建てられた収容所には、 バラック以外何もなく、
日系人たちは生活に必要なものすべてを
自分たちの手で作らなければなりませんでした。
昼は灼熱の太陽が照りつけ、 夜は凍てつく寒さが襲います。
ひとたび砂嵐が吹き始めると、 一週間もの間吹き荒れました。
I was fighting the fine sand that
penetrated through the gaps in the
barracks all day long.
土凍る高原の夜の寒さ肌を刺す
八雲たらずみぞれふる鉄椒
七人連れの囚われの旅に 心身共に疲れ果てたる サンタアナよりの人々
Ina gakkari shite, erai toko ni
hairimashite, nan ni mo nai, ki ga nai,
hitotsu mo ganbatte
nai. Dakar papa, do shite mo yama no hon
ni minasai, me o ati no hon ni minasai.
Kirei na sunset, sunrise ga aru ka, do
shite mo nature ga yoku suru. Shizen ga. I
worked hard to improve my spirit and my
feelings.
Obata Chiura was convinced that looking at
the beautiful nature leads to hope for
tomorrow. 確信していました。
収容所のシンボルである給水塔と夕日を受けて朱に染まった雲。
過酷な条件の中で千浦の美術学校に込めた思いが感じられる作品です。
Topaz Art School opened several art
exhibitions before the end of the war.
From Tampolan to Topaz, there were friends
who supported the art school started by
Obata Chura.
日系二世の美音大久保
カリフォルニア大学バークレー校の美術学生だった彼女は
タンホラン美術学校ではチューラと共に教師として参加しました
Mine Okubo uses wood to depict the world
of despair and suffering.
日比久子は母親の視点から収容所の中の生活を細やかに描いています。
トパーズ農場の収穫物
作品の裏には砂漠の荒野で果物と野菜を育て
届けてくれたトパーズの日本人農民に捧げると書かれています
Hibi Shisako's husband, Hibi Matsusaburo,
often appears in his works.
Koyote is a symbol
of freedom that we should be envious of,
Hibi Matsusaburo was a close friend of
Obata Chura since he had just arrived in
Japan. Han was a trusted friend from a
young age. He was an indispensable
collaborator from Tannhoran to Topaz to
run the art school.
When we established Tannhoran Art School,
Chiura consulted daily. The art school was
established with the cooperation of the
two.
学校ができ生徒が来るかどうか 二人は心配するわけですけども
ちょうど開校の日は大嵐になって
冷たい雨が降っていたんです
その雨の中に三人の小さな女の子が
ポツンと立ってドアを開くのを待ってた
二人はその子供たちを教室の中に入れて
Hervo JOY Japanese
Hiyon Kim Taewoo
Min
Hwasa トパーズの夕暮れに絵を描く男たち。
勇士鉄線の中にいても絵を描くことができる喜びが後姿に現れています。
I noticed that drawing his paintings has
become his way of life. Dat He is also
fairly talented today.
Dan Harada san, 72 saig. Nikkei nisei to
shite, 19 saig no toki ni shuyo sa
remashita.
Harada san wa, hibi Matsusaburo ni,
kyanbas wo haru koto kara shido wo uke, e
wo kaku koto ni nomirikonde ikimashita.
1943年に行われたアメリカへの忠誠を問うテストが原田さんの運命を変えましたその質問は天皇への忠誠を否定できるか命令を受けた場合アメリカ軍人として戦う意思はあるか原田さんはこれらの質問にノーと答えました
Det導 Everyone knew I had anuszka. I had
been sent to the wonderful manor WZ
TURU REIKU SHUYUJO
Harada-san walked in the camp at night,
and he said that it looked as if the barak
were lonely, and that it was like they
were himself.
What does the era of the camp mean to you?
I think it's a very... Even now, it's
very... How should I put it?
In my heart, it's a wound, but at the same
time, for me, it's a very creative, above
all else, I was able to create and create
my own art.
The four years
of the school were full of humiliation for
the Nikkei people.
But it was no doubt that the art school
became a source of life.
1945年8月14日 日本時間8月15日
日比松桜は終戦のこの日に一枚の絵を残しています
そこには祖国のある西に向かって
神戸を垂れている一人の男が描かれています
廃墟
尾端千浦が広島に落とされた原爆のニュースを聞いて書いた作品です。
Obata Chiura never painted the last
picture of this war.
戦後なんですが、尾端千代は大学に復職しまして、
バークレー校の名誉教授を務めた後、退職するんですね。
その後は文化の架け橋としてアメリカに日本の文化を紹介するということに人生を捧げたんですね。
文化の架け橋ということでいうと、たくさんの画家たちがアメリカに渡って、
国と国との間の文化を結ぼうとするわけですけど、
それが国と国との戦争という運命によって、
ああいう強制収容所のようなのが入れられてしまう。
Oubata Chura and Hibi Matsubara created a
very large movement, the art school. It
was very powerful and valuable.
I think it was as valuable as Dan Harada
or Mino Okubo's work. I think it was very
valuable to change it somehow.
意志みたいなものは非常に貴重だなって気がしますね。
それにしてもトパーズの旧正秋葉原の後に言ったんですけど、
本当に猛烈な風で、あの日ちょうど気温が38度でしてね、
もうちょっとこういうだけで日差しが本当に強くて、 じりじり痛いくらいなんですよね。
あれだけの過酷な厳しい条件の中でも、 絶望しないで絵を描き続けたと。
非常に強靭な精神力ですかね、それを思うんですが、
でも一方で絵を見ますと、非常に透明感がある、 伸びやかな絵も非常に多いんですよね。
透明感というものが、本当に京成修行の中での ある種の高い志と言いましょうか、
志を表すものなのかな、そういう思いをして 描いてきたんですけれどもね。
尾形千代の絵の特質というのは、 やはり大胆で軽やかなところだと思うんですよね。
母なる大地のようなところで緻密な日本画の技法があるんですが、それを遥かにこうやって、
心情までも表すような、修正表現主義のような形というものがあって、
その軽やかさが、そういう意味でいうと、希望をもたらすというか、そういう感じがあったんだろうなという気がしますね。
その象徴的な色がチューラブルーですか、真っ青なカリフォルニアの青と、チューラブルー。本当に印象的でしたけどもね。
中羅の作品は日本で初公開ですが、
中羅の作品多数を含めますアメリカに生きた日系人画家たちの展覧会、
10月1日までですが、東京都の庭園美術館で開かれています。
その後、大分と広島でも開かれる予定になっています。
Undertexter av Nicolai Winther
Undertexter av
Undertexter av Nicolai
Winther
Undertexter av Nicolai Winther
Undertexter av
Undertexter av Nicolai Winther Næ humility
the
powerhide and When you touch the switch,
your heart
will be like this. That's the title of the
game.
This time it's a self-destruction. It's
interesting. I wonder if the robot is
waiting for someone. I'm frustrated. I
step on the ground. It looks like I'm
stepping on a tap. It feels very humorous.
N'amara Made This piece is the movement by
moisng by moving it Server! sozusagen
영어심트動きは SOW。 同じく上空規管によるものです。
斜めまで同時の作品は、上記や重りといった、
最近ではおなじみることの見つまった動力と、
神秘な仕組み、そして愛情のあるコルミで、 見るならも好奇心を知るでしょう。
これシデロイホスと作品の題ですけどもね これギリシャ語で鉄の響き
まさに鉄の響きという意味なんだそうですね
ちょっととぼけたいい音ではありますね
This is a sound of a bow being pulled.
It's a sound with a very cosmic secret.
It's a sound that you can't usually hear.
Undertexter av
Undertekster av Ai-Media
Undertexter av Nicolai
Winther